Okay, today we start on top of י"א ע"א, Yud Aleph Amud
Aleph, בכורות Bechorot 10a, and we have been in the middle of
discussing the issue that, you know, the Torah talks about redeeming the
firstborn donkey but does not tell you what the status of the
sheep is, doesn't tell you what the status of the donkey is,
doesn't tell you anything about whether it has any status. So the
גמרא Gemara starts with assuming that the sheep is not sanctified, is
just the כהן's Kohen property, and then the question is what is
the status of the donkey before it was redeemed. And it said
that was a debate between רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון.
Rebbe Shimon. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said that it was sanctified because
you normally don't have a redemption on a non-sanctified, it was forbidden
in benefit, the act of redemption wouldn't be meaningful unless it was
coming to remove a status, although the counterproof to that was of
course firstborn humans. And רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon said no, it has
no status, you do have a מצוה Mitzvah to redeem it but
it has no status, okay, the donkey. Now, what happens if you
actually did not redeem it and you went ahead and broke its
neck? So there the גמרא Gemara is been claiming that רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon would admit that there after the neck is broken that
it is forbidden in benefit because of the comparison to the broken
neck of the עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah. And we are now going
to spend the rest of today's דף Daf trying to prove that
or hear different opinions about that, about whether רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
would say that after you break the neck whether the donkey is
forbidden or not. The initial proof is a ברייתא Braita where there's
a question about things that are forbidden in benefit, like a שור
הנסקל Shor Haniskal and an עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah and other things,
and including this donkey whose neck is broken. And the question is
whether they're considered food or not for the טומאה Tumah of food,
for receiving the impurity of foods if they touch something טמא. Tamei.
So the Rabbis say that it is considered food because it's physically
edible, and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says it's not food because a
Jew cannot eat it and a Jew cannot even feed it to
a non-Jew. A non-Jew may be allowed to eat it but a
Jew cannot give it to a non-Jew. So another way of saying
it is that the Rabbis say that it is physically edible and
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says halachically it's not edible, not only by
you but you can't even make it give it to somebody else
to eat. And among those lists, while right now we're focusing on
the fact that he mentioned meat and milk, so we'll pick up
with that, but in that list also was the broken-necked donkey. So
that seems to prove the fact that that is the point of
debate between him and the Rabbis, that seems to prove that that
is another example that is something that is forbidden in benefit even
according to רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. So let's pick up at the
top of י"א ע"א. Yud Aleph Amud Aleph. Now, the one exception
that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon had where he admitted that something was
food even though it was not forbidden even though it was forbidden
in benefit was בשר בחלב, Basar Bechalav, meat and milk. Why? Because
meat and milk started off being food before you cooked them together.
So before they became forbidden they started as being food, therefore they
retain their status. Now the גמרא Gemara says top of י"א ע"א,
Yud Aleph Amud Aleph, ליהכי, Lihachi, if that's true, בשר בחלב, Basar
Bechalav, אמאי אירייא דהויא ליה שעת כושר, Amai irya dehavya lei sha'at
kosher,
why are we emphasizing by בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav that the reason
it is considered food according to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon is because
at what time it was edible before you cooked it together? תיפוק
ליה דחזיא לאכילת עובד כוכבים, Tipok lei dechazya l'achilat oved kochavim, you
can give it to other people to eat. Now why can you
give it to a non-Jew to eat? Isn't meat and milk forbidden
in benefit? But guess what, the same רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon, thank
you, the same רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon that says that is the
one here that talks about things that are forbidden in benefit are
not food, is the רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon that says that בשר
בחלב Basar Bechalav cooked together is מותר בהנאה, Mutar Behana'ah, permissible in
benefit. It's an opinion that is a very minor opinion but it
is the opinion of the same רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר, Rebbe
Shimon ben Yehuda omer, רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rebbe Shimon ben Yehuda
says, משום רבי שמעון, Mishum Rebbe Shimon, from the original רבי שמעון,
Rebbe Shimon, from the classic רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon, classic רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon is רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rebbe Shimon bar Yochai. So
what do we taught in the name of רבי שמעון? Rebbe Shimon?
בשר בחלב אסור באכילה ומותר בהנאה, Basar Bechalav asur ba'achilah u'mutar behana'ah,
meat and milk cooked together is not only is forbidden to be
eaten but actually you can derive benefit. By the way, we spent
a lot of time talking about this when we learned חולין, Chullin,
but just to point out to you how relevant this is, is
a big question about buying dog food or cat food which very
often is meat and milk cooked together. If it's forbidden in benefit
you cannot buy it and feed it to your cat or dog.
So we rule that meat and milk is forbidden in benefit, but
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says it's permissible. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse
says, כי עם קדוש אתה לה' אלקיך, Ki am kadosh atah l'Hashem
Elokecha, you are a holy people to Hashem your God, and it
ends לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו, Lo tevashel gedi bachalev imo, do
not cook meat and milk together. ולהלן הוא אומר, U'lehalan hu omer,
and in another verse it says, ואנשי קדש תהיון לי, V'Anshei Kodesh
Tihyun Li, you shall be a holy people to me, ובשר בשדה
טרפה לא תאכלו לכלב תשליכון אתו, U'Basar Basadeh Treifah Lo Tocheilu Lakalev
Tashlichun Oto, do not eat treif meat, meat torn, you know, torn
by an animal, meat that is a טרפה, Treifah, and the end
of the verse says give it to the dogs. So the Torah
is explicit that טרפה Treifah meat is מותר בהנאה, Mutar Behana'ah,
you can derive benefit, and it uses the same phrase of holiness.
So if it's linked to meat and milk, we should say meat
and milk also you can derive benefit. So רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
says you can derive benefit from meat and milk. So now we've
got a question, why does רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon say the reason
meat and milk is considered food is because at one stage it
was permissible? Tell us that even now it's permissible in benefit and
can be fed to non-Jews and therefore it should be considered food.
One
reason I'll
agree that meat and milk is considered food is חדא דהא חזיא
דאתה יכול להאכילה לנכרי הוא, chada de-ha chazya de-ata yachol le-achila le-nachri
hu,
that even if we assume it's forbidden in benefit, it can be
eaten by non-Jews... I skipped that. One reason is because I personally
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon hold that it is not forbidden in benefit,
and therefore non-Jews can eat it and therefore you can give it
to non-Jews, and therefore it is considered food. So that's number one
because I personally hold that it is not forbidden in benefit. ועוד
ve-od
and in addition, even according to the general assumption that meat and
milk is forbidden in benefit, לדידי נמי הרי היתה לה שעת הכושר,
le-didi nami harei hayta la-sha'at ha-kosher,
it had actually a time when it was permissible in... when it
was food before you cooked them together. So that is the issue
of meat and milk. So what do we have? רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, we have a whole list of things that are forbidden in
benefit. The Rabbis say it's considered food for laws of טומאת אוכלין.
tum'at ochlin. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's not considered food. Why
is it not considered food? Because you're not allowed to eat it
and you're not allowed to give it to somebody to eat as
a Jew. A non-Jew might be allowed to eat it but you
can't give it because you can't derive benefit. The one thing I
admit to is meat and milk. Why do I admit meat and
milk is considered food? Because it started off being food. When it
was just meat and just milk before you cooked them together. So
even though now it might be forbidden in benefit, it still retains
its status of food. And then the גמרא Gemara says, oh, but
actually I don't even need that reason because I personally רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon hold that meat and milk is permissible in benefit. So
you are allowed to feed it to non-Jews anyway. But there's two
reasons why I will admit that meat and milk is considered food.
Number one, it started as food. Number two, I personally would hold
that you can feed it to non-Jews. But normal things that are
forbidden in benefit, since you can't eat them and you can't give
it to a non-Jew to eat, therefore is not food. And in
that list is the broken-necked donkey. So you see that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon admits, although he says a donkey is permissible in benefit,
he admits that once you break the neck, it's forbidden in benefit.
Yes.
What about עגלה ערופה? egla arufa? Had a time when you could
eat it.
No, because it was never meat. I mean, it had a time
when it could have been maybe shechted, but it was never edible.
Meat and milk were actually edible. Okay, so yeah. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues.
So it says like this: ואם איתא, ve-im ita, if it were
true, דאחר עריפה שרי רבי שמעון, de-achar arifa shari Rabbi Shimon, that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would admit that even after breaking the neck,
the donkey would remain permissible, לתני, lisni, why don't we teach, מודה
רבי שמעון בפטר חמור ובשר בחלב שמטמא
טומאת אוכלין? modeh Rabbi Shimon be-peter chamor u-basar be-chalav she-metame tum'at ochlin?
Why does he only concede the point of meat and milk? He
should admit even not only by meat and milk is considered food,
but he should even admit that the broken-necked donkey is considered food
because it is permissible in benefit. Now, not that a Jew can
eat it, I mean, you know, it's donkey meat, but you can...
a non-Jew can eat it and if it's permissible in benefit, a
Jew who owns it can give it to a non-Jew as a
gift, can sell it to a non-Jew, is allowed to feed it
to a non-Jew. So the fact that he says the broken-necked donkey
is not food shows that he holds that at least by the
time you break its neck, it is forbidden in benefit. Seems to
be a very good straightforward proof, but the גמרא Gemara is going
to try to get out of it by saying that might be
a very special reason that the donkey is forbidden... is not food.
Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: הכא
במאי עסקינן... hacha be-mai askinan... אי דחשיב ליה, i de-chashiv lei, if
you planned on eating the donkey meat, הכא נמי, hacha nami,
then maybe he would say that it is food or you planned
on giving it to a non-Jew to eat, he would admit that
it is food. Maybe he says that the donkey is actually permissible
in benefit. So why does he say it's not considered food? But
הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, what are we talking about here?
דלא חשיב ליה, de-lo chashiv lei, that the reason why it's not
food is because it's donkey meat and you did not plan on
eating it. Meaning, if you remember we had this a few days
ago about like honey of a wasps or whatever other animals, there's
some types of things that are totally permissible to be eaten, but
because it's not the norm to be eaten, they do not have
the halakhic status of food unless you plan on eating it. So
here we have in this ברייתא, baraita, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon implicitly
says that donkey meat is... is not edible. And presumably the reason
is because it's forbidden in הנאה hana'ah and it shows that he
meets... he admits that when you break the neck of the donkey,
it's forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, and that's therefore it's not edible.
The גמרא Gemara says no, no, no, maybe although all the other
things the reason he's saying aren't food is because you can't get
benefit, this maybe is a special case. You know why the... the
donkey meat is... is not food? Because what type of a person
eats donkey meat? And therefore, right, totally agree, therefore since you normally
wouldn't eat it and you normally wouldn't even give it to a
non-Jew to eat and you're not planning on treating it as food,
so that's why he says that it's not true. Now of course
it's very bizarre because then it has nothing to do with the
broken-necked donkey. He could have just said any... any donkey meat. So
it's a very like weird... way, you know, sort of a very,
you know, very... the גמרא Gemara really tries to... to narrow the...
or to redefine the parameters of the case in order to get
out of it. But certainly the obvious evidence here is that he
admits
that
the
donkey...
. "peter chamor" פטר חמור. peter chamor. "Mishnah" משנה. Mishnah. "Rashi" רש"י.
Rashi.
"Torah" תורה. Torah. "Gemara" גמרא. Gemara. "Rishonim" ראשונים. Rishonim. "Rabbi Shimon" רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. "Rav Sheshet" רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. "v'taama mai" וטעמא
מאי. v'taama mai. "amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet" אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב
ששת. amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet. "ho'il v'issuro chishuvo" הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו.
ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro chishuvo" ורבנן מי אמרי
הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'ha tnan" והתנן.
v'ha tnan. "Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru" שלש עשרה דברים נאמרו. Shelosh esrei
devarim ne'emru. "amru" אמרו. amru. "b'nivlat of
tahor" בנבלת עוף טהור. b'nivlat of tahor. "shechted"
שחוטה. shechted. "tumah" טומאה. tumah. "tamei" טמא. tamei. "peter chamor" פטר חמור.
peter chamor. "Mishnah" משנה. Mishnah. "Rashi" רש"י. Rashi. "Torah" תורה. Torah. "Gemara"
גמרא. Gemara. "Rishonim" ראשונים. Rishonim. "Rabbi Shimon" רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. "Rav
Sheshet" רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. "v'taama mai" וטעמא מאי. v'taama mai. "amru
rabanan kamei
d'Rav Sheshet" אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב ששת. amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet.
"ho'il v'issuro chishuvo" הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'rabanan mi amri
ho'il v'issuro chishuvo" ורבנן מי אמרי הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. v'rabanan mi amri
ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'ha tnan" והתנן. v'ha tnan. "Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru"
שלש עשרה
דברים
נאמרו. Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru. "amru" אמרו. amru. "b'nivlat of
tahor" בנבלת עוף טהור. b'nivlat of tahor. "shechted" שחוטה. shechted. "tumah" טומאה.
tumah. "tamei" טמא. tamei. "peter chamor" פטר חמור. peter chamor. "Mishnah" משנה.
Mishnah. "Rashi" רש"י. Rashi. "Torah" תורה. Torah. "Gemara" גמרא. Gemara. "Rishonim" ראשונים.
Rishonim. "Rabbi Shimon" רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. "Rav Sheshet" רב ששת. Rav
Sheshet. "v'taama mai" וטעמא מאי. v'taama mai. "amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet"
אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב ששת. amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet. "ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo" הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo" ורבנן מי אמרי הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo. "v'ha tnan" והתנן. v'ha tnan. "Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru" שלש עשרה
דברים נאמרו. Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru. "amru" אמרו. amru. "b'nivlat of tahor"
בנבלת עוף טהור. b'nivlat of tahor. "shechted" שחוטה. shechted. "tumah" טומאה. tumah.
"tamei" טמא. tamei. "peter chamor" פטר חמור. peter chamor. "Mishnah" משנה. Mishnah.
"Rashi" רש"י. Rashi. "Torah" תורה. Torah. "Gemara" גמרא. Gemara. "Rishonim" ראשונים. Rishonim.
"Rabbi Shimon" רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. "Rav Sheshet" רב ששת. Rav Sheshet.
"v'taama mai" וטעמא מאי. v'taama mai. "amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet" אמרו
רבנן קמיה דרב ששת. amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet. "ho'il v'issuro chishuvo"
הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro chishuvo"
ורבנן מי אמרי הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro chishuvo.
"v'ha tnan" והתנן. v'ha tnan. "Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru" שלש עשרה דברים
נאמרו. Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru. "amru" אמרו. amru. "b'nivlat of
tahor" בנבלת עוף טהור. b'nivlat of tahor. "shechted" שחוטה. shechted. "tumah" טומאה.
tumah. "tamei" טמא. tamei. "peter chamor" פטר חמור. peter chamor. "Mishnah" משנה.
Mishnah. "Rashi" רש"י. Rashi. "Torah" תורה. Torah. "Gemara" גמרא. Gemara. "Rishonim" ראשונים.
Rishonim. "Rabbi Shimon" רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. "Rav Sheshet" רב ששת. Rav
Sheshet. "v'taama mai" וטעמא מאי. v'taama mai. "amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet"
אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב ששת. amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet. "ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo" הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo" ורבנן מי אמרי הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo. "v'ha tnan" והתנן. v'ha tnan. "Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru" שלש עשרה
דברים נאמרו. Shelosh esrei devarim ne'emru. "amru" אמרו. amru. "b'nivlat of
tahor" בנבלת עוף טהור. b'nivlat of tahor. "shechted" שחוטה. shechted. "tumah" טומאה.
tumah. "tamei" טמא. tamei. "peter chamor" פטר חמור. peter chamor. "Mishnah" משנה.
Mishnah. "Rashi" רש"י. Rashi. "Torah" תורה. Torah. "Gemara" גמרא. Gemara. "Rishonim" ראשונים.
Rishonim. "Rabbi Shimon" רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. "Rav Sheshet" רב ששת. Rav
Sheshet. "v'taama mai" וטעמא מאי. v'taama mai. "amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet"
אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב ששת. amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Sheshet. "ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo" הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. ho'il v'issuro chishuvo. "v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo" ורבנן מי אמרי הואיל ואיסורו חשיבותו. v'rabanan mi amri ho'il v'issuro
chishuvo. "v'ha tnan" והתנן Thirteen things were said about this carcass of
a כשר kosher bird, וזו אחת מהן, v'zu achas meihen, this is
one of them. צריכה מחשבה, tzrichah machshavah, in order to be considered
food you have to plan on eating it, I guess normal people
would not eat the carcass of a dead
bird, ואינה צריכה הכשר, v'einah tzrichah hechsheir, but it does not have
to come into contact with water. Right, remember for food to be
susceptible for טומאה tumah it has to come in contact with water.
Why do you not need this by the carcass of a dead
bird? Because this is a special exception, right, you might remember this,
we did this a few weeks ago, that if something will in
the end be a source of טומאה, tumah, then even though now
it is not yet a source of טומאה, tumah, but if that's
its future or its possible future, then right now it does not
need contact with water to become susceptible. So if I were to
swallow this carcass of a chicken, let's say, while it was going
down my throat, it would make me טמא. tamei. So even but
touching it does not, but eating it does. Since this carcass of
a chicken therefore can in the future be a source of טומאה,
tumah, then right now it does not need contact with liquid in
order to become טמא. tamei. But it does need to be considered
food, and it's not food unless I actually plan on eating it,
because normal people don't eat, you know, chickens that died naturally. Okay,
normal carcasses of dead chickens are not normal things people eat, and
because normally, you know, whatever, they're smelly, they would die of old
age or of disease or whatever it might be, and therefore it
will only be food once I plan on eating it. And now
of course so the question is going to be, but why don't
we say by virtue of the fact that the תורה Torah forbids
a carcass in eating, automatically makes it food? If the rabbis really
hold that anything that is halachically forbidden to eat, by definition is
being acknowledged as food by the fact that it's being forbidden. Yes.
But the way that most animals are slaughtered today and birds, they
become נבילה neveilah because they don't have a proper
שחיטה. shechitah. That's true in ancient times as well.
That's an interesting question. Right, the assumption here that you would not
normally eat it because it, you're right, like נבילה neveilah here probably
refers to the sort of sense of like dying on its own.
Right. But yeah, that's a good point. Like would you say the
same thing that a bird slaughtered but not slaughtered properly, but slaughtered
דווקא davka by non-Jews in the process of making it food or
whatever, why would you say that that type of a thing would
start to become נבילה? neveilah? Yeah, for us that's a נבילה. neveilah.
Right, right, right. That's a good point. I don't know if that
may be that, you know, I could imagine that there could be
a distinction made about that point. It's a very good point. But
right now at least presumably we're talking about something that died naturally.
So let's take a look.
Okay.
Yes. Something that died naturally you don't eat, but something we murdered
we do.
Well,
but normally because things that we die naturally often die as a
result of disease, and we also don't control the environment, you know,
so it can get all buggy and rotten and whatever.
But let's say a branch fell on the top of the head
of something we would have eaten, and the animal died. It didn't
die of disease, we saw the animal die, we know it didn't
die of disease.
Right, right. So that's right, that's a variation of Charlie's question. Why
do we lump all נבילה neveilah in the same category? If right,
that's a very good point. I have to see if anybody makes
a distinction. But let's but now the גמרא's Gemara immediate concern is
that even if we grant that normal people don't eat it, why
don't we say if it's forbidden that makes it considered food? So
the גמרא Gemara says, ואי איסורו חשיבותיה, v'ei issuro chashivuteih,
if if its forbiddenness makes it significant, למה לי מחשבה, lamah li
machshavah, why do I have to want to eat this corpse of
the bird? By virtue of it being forbidden and a נבילה neveilah
should define it as food. The גמרא Gemara says, you know what,
you're right, but הא מני רבי שמעון היא, ha mani Rabbi Shimon
hi, that would be רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. We just said that
that was the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the rabbis,
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon just says nobody eats it, and the
rabbis say no, no, no, it gets its food status by virtue
of being forbidden. So if you have a proof that somebody says,
you know, it's nobody eats it, it's not a problem, that's רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. You, you know, you say, well, don't we say
if it's forbidden that makes it food? That's the rabbis. We don't
have to say that this teaching is the rabbis. This teaching could
be רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. I should also point out by the
way that there's a little irony, that the basic debate of רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the rabbis is that the rabbis say if
something is physically edible it's food, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
if it's forbidden in benefit it's not. So there רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon looks at the halachic status to define it as food, and
the rabbis look at the practical aspect. What the גמרא Gemara is
now suggesting, and again the גמרא's Gemara going to reject it, but
what the גמרא's Gemara now suggesting is almost a reversal, not really,
but like logically it's the opposite positions. The rabbis say, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says since this I don't know dead bird is edible
it's food, and the rabbis say, I'm sorry, since excuse me, since
this dead bird normal people don't eat it, it's not food, so
he's going by the practical reality about how it is eaten or
not eaten, and the rabbis go by the halachic reality. Since it's
forbidden, that forbidden nature defines it as food. Now it's not really
the reverse, because normally רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says the more forbidden
it is the less it's food, and the rabbis are saying here
the more forbidden it is the more it's food, but nevertheless in
one case the rabbis look at the physical and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon looks at the halachic, and in the other case they sort
of swap it. Okay, but now we are working with that idea
that according to the rabbis by virtue of something being forbidden to
be eaten, that implicitly defines it as food. So let's let's keep
on going.
תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, נבילת בהמה טמאה בכל מקום
neveilas beheimah tmeiah b'chol makom ונבילת v'neveilas of a dead non-kosher animal,
so that would be like a חמור, chamor, a donkey, okay, or
a horse or whatever, anywhere, you
know, whether it's in the villages or in the city, normal people
don't eat that. It's has two things going against it. Number one,
it's a non-kosher animal and number two, it's a נבלה. neveilah. Now
non-Jews really don't care about the non-kosher animal part. תוספות Tosafot actually
even points out that there's other evidence that non-Jews, you know, you
know, particularly let's say one of the things that's a classic non-kosher
animal is a pig. And there's evidence that non-Jews and, you know,
we know from our society that's very high up on the desirability
meat. So one of the interesting things about this, about why it's
not considered food, again, and this gets to this issue, halakhic or
or physical reality, you know, whatever, or the reality, is the fact
that there are two things that make it forbidden. A, it's not
kosher, and B, it's a נבלה. neveilah. So, you know, so that
more pushes it out of the category of food. So again, you
know, this is always the question: what makes something considered food or
not food? The fact that is it halakhic status or is it
the fact that in practice it is or is not eaten? So
here we have a cork, a carcass of a non-kosher animal, which
is considered not food, either because nobody eats it or because it's
doubly forbidden. And not only that, ונבלת עוף הטהור, unevelas of hatahor,
the carcass of a dead bird, which we've already seen is not
normally eaten, even though it's a kosher bird. I'm going to take
out the word חלב, chelev, fat, because רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
both point out it doesn't really fit, so we'll skip over that
for now. בכפרים, bikvarim, in the villages. So in the cities where
there is a higher demand, people will eat a wider range of
meat. So people will eat carcasses of dead kosher birds, but in
the villages where there's a much slower demand, people are not going
to eat, you know, dead birds, they have plenty of meat to
eat anyway. So in those places, a carcass of a dead of
a non-kosher animal and a carcass of a bird anywhere, and a
carcass of a bird in the villages are places where normally those
things are not eaten. So since those are normally not eaten, צריכים
מחשבה, tzerichim machshavah, in order to be considered food, you have to
plan eating it. Normally we would say it's not eaten. ואינם צריכים
הכשר, ve'einam tzerichim hechsher, they don't have to come in contact with
liquid. Why not? Because again, what's the principle? If something is or
will be the source of טומאה, tumah, it does not need contact
with liquid to be considered susceptible. So a carcass of a non-kosher
animal, a carcass of a kosher animal is a source of טומאה
tumah and therefore does not need contact with liquid, okay? So again,
the reason, the purpose of these משניות mishnayot are all saying the
basic same point, which is something that's not normally eaten, you need
to have intention to eat it in order to make it food.
Does it need to come in contact with liquid? Only if it
will never be a source of טומאה. tumah. If it will be
a source of טומאה tumah or is a source of טומאה tumah
like these cases, it does not need contact with liquid. Now our
point though is, forget the contact with liquid and the הכשר. hechsher.
We are talking about non-kosher animals and we're saying that since normally
they're not eaten, you need intention in order to make them food.
But didn't you just tell me that the Rabbis say that anything
that is forbidden in eating, by virtue of being made forbidden, tells
you that we're talking, we're considering it to be food? So why
here does it need מחשבה, machshavah, does it need intention? So the
גמרא Gemara says, ואי אמרת, ve'i amart, if you said,
איסורו חשיבותו, issuro chishuvo, its forbidden nature gives it status and makes
it food, למה לי מחשבה, lama li machshavah, why do I have
to plan to eat the carcass of this non-kosher animal? Ha, so
the fact that it's forbidden, by definition defines it as food. So
the גמרא Gemara says, הא מני רבי שמעון היא, ha mani Rebbe
Shimon hi, again, this is רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. We only claimed
that the Rabbis held that since something was forbidden it made it
food. This is רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon and therefore that's why, that's
why you need to intend to eat it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear, and it's basically going
to be the same proof, but here it's going to be clear
that it is not רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon's position. So תא שמע,
ta shma, come and
hear: נבלת בהמה טהורה, nevelas behemah tehorah, this is basically the flip
of what we just said before, the carcass of a kosher animal,
like a dead cow, בכל מקום, bechol makom, anywhere, normally that would
be something that people would eat, a dead cow, even if it
died naturally. Somehow dead, somehow carcasses of dead cows are more edible
than carcasses of dead birds. I guess it is true that, you
know, birds get smelly and disgusting much easier with all the feathers
and they're smaller, it's easier to be trampled on. So anyway, so
the carcass of a dead cow is something that you don't need
to want, intend to eat, it more naturally is eaten anyway and
does not need מחשבה. machshavah. So the carcass of a dead cow,
בכל מקום, bechol makom, anywhere, ונבלת עוף הטהור והחלב בשווקים, unevelas of
hatahor vehachelev bishvakim, or the carcass of a dead bird or fat
in the בשווקים, shvakim, means like the, what do you call it,
the marketplace, the cities. So that's a place where there is a
higher demand, so they'll be more prepared to eat it. In the
villages they won't eat it, but in the cities they will eat
it. So under those contexts, these are things that do not need
מחשבה. machshavah. אינם צריכים מחשבה, einam tzerichim machshavah, they do not need
intention to be considered food, these are things that are normally eaten.
A carcass of a dead cow anywhere and a carcass of a
dead bird at least in the cities. I'm not going to talk
about חלב, chelev, which makes it a little more complicated. ולא הכשר,
velo hechsher, they do not need contact with liquid again because they
are the source of טומאה. tumah. חלב chelev again is a little
different, but we're not going into that. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
like this: הטמאה. hatemeiah. So that basically is the exact same, right?
It’s the parallel image. The first said carcass of a non-kosher animal
and carcasses of birds in the village does need מחשבה. machshavah. This
is the other half of that. Carcass of a kosher animal and
the carcass of birds in cities does not need מחשבה. machshavah. So
basically it’s the exact same statement. But the reason it’s another question
is because Rabbi Shimon’s position becomes clear here. So the גמרא Gemara
says הטמאה hatemeiah implicitly that’s saying that if it were the carcass
of a non-kosher animal, בעי מחשבה, ba’ei machshavah, it would require intention
to make it considered food and we would not say that by
virtue of being forbidden it’s considered food. Now your standard answer is
going to be, okay, that’s Rabbi Shimon. וכי תימא המני רבי שמעון,
v’chi teima haman Rabbi Shimon, that’s Rabbi Shimon. Rabbi Shimon doesn’t hold
of this principle that since it’s forbidden it makes it food. One
minute. הא מדסיפא רבי שמעון היא רישא לאו רבי שמעון היא. ha
mi-de-seifa Rabbi Shimon haviya reisha lav Rabbi Shimon. Ha! Here I caught
you. Here you can’t get out of it by claiming it’s Rabbi
Shimon because the end of this says explicitly an opposing position of
Rabbi Shimon. So it’s clear the beginning is a non-Rabbi Shimon position.
Where does the end say Rabbi Shimon’s position? דקתני סיפא, de-katani seifa,
we teach at the end, רבי שמעון אומר אף הגמל והארנבת והשפן
והחזיר, Rabbi Shimon omer af ha-gamal ve-ha-arnevet ve-ha-shafan ve-ha-chazir, even the גמל
camel and the ארנבת arnevet and the שפן, shafan, which are two
types of hares and rabbits or whatever, and the חזיר, chazir, the
pig, אינם צריכים לא מחשבה ולא הכשר. einam tzerichim lo machshavah ve-lo
hechsher. Do not need intention to define them as food, they don’t
need liquid because obviously they are נבילה. neveilah. But why don’t they
need intention? He says, you Rabbis, you say the carcass of non-kosher
animals requires intention. I don’t agree with you. I say that there
are some non-kosher animals that their carcass is considered food even without
intention, like the camel and the rabbit and the pig. Now why
would he say that? He could just say practically these are things
people eat. I don’t know, people definitely eat rabbit meat and pig
meat. Do they eat camel meat? Camel meat too?
I’ve heard of camel milk.
Okay, camel milk, but we’re
talking- I’ve never heard of camel meat being eaten.
Okay, anyway, so here he’s saying, you say carcasses of non-kosher animals
normally are not food, I’m going to say these non-kosher animals are
food even without intention. It could just be they’re arguing practically what
people eat, eat it, but the גמרא Gemara interestingly here adds a
הלכה halakhic aspect as well. Let’s take a look. ואמר רבי שמעון,
v’amar Rabbi Shimon, or now Rabbi Shimon says, מה טעם, ma ta’am,
what’s the reason I say this? הואיל ויש בהן סימן טהרה. ho’il
ve-yesh bahen siman taharah.
These are non-kosher animals that have at least one kosher סימן, siman,
right? The pig has the split hooves, these other animals too they
chew their cud. So therefore, since they are not totally, you know,
outside of the boundaries of kosher animals, it’s easier to consider them
as food. So I should mention by the way, we’re introducing a
new idea. It’s- I mean what’s sort of interesting, I know it’s
you can get sort of caught up in who’s saying what here,
but the themes are very important, meaning we started with the theme
of that Rabbi Shimon- something that can be eaten but is forbidden
in benefit. Does the הלכה halakhic status of forbidden in benefit make
it not food or do you go by the practical ability to
be eaten? Then we introduced somewhat of a reverse idea. Not that
the being forbidden makes it not food, but maybe being forbidden to
eat, not let’s say benefit, but to eat, defines it as food.
You don’t make something forbidden to eat unless you’re acknowledging it as
food. Now we’re actually saying also that there’s some types of things
which could be food, but do you need to intend to eat
them or not? So here we’re saying, well, if it’s like fully
forbidden, it has two non-kosher סימנים, simanim, like it’s a donkey and
it’s a carcass, that’s so much הלכה halakhically pushed away from Jews
at least that that’s totally non-food unless you plan on eating it.
But then Rabbi Shimon says, okay, but if it’s not that far
out, if it’s only one non-kosher סימן, siman, so it’s somewhat in
the conversation, that is more considered in the category of food. So
it’s interesting whether what are we looking at to define? Are we
just looking at the practice of what people do? Are we looking
at what how the הלכה halakhah allows me to do things? Are
we looking about like how far or close, you know, the הלכה
halakhah places this to define whether this is considered to be food
or not? So that’s like the ongoing question here about how much
does the definition of food go by in practice what I do
or am able to do, or does it go by status that
is defined through the הלכה? halakhah? And if it’s through the הלכה,
halakhah, it could be either if it’s forbidden in benefit it’s not
food, it could be if it’s only forbidden in eating by virtue
of being forbidden in eating that’s saying that it is food, it
could be that if it’s doubly forbidden it’s not food, but if
it has some kosher aspects to it, that does make it more
food. So that’s all within the question of its הלכה halakhic status,
not its practical status defining it as food or not. Yes, Charles?
Does that- time something is food or not might have some practical
status today, for instance we have as I mentioned,
food colorings that are made from ground up insects. Right. Is that
food? Yes, it’s not- nobody eats insects.
Right, so that’s a good point.
So- that’s true by the way, they’re okay.
So first of all it’s not true, right, there are now insectivores
and whatever and that’s a whole new delicacy. But the other point
is, and that’s- this is an important point. We did mention the
other day things that were not food like beeswax. shellac or whatever.
But when I'm saying food or not food, yeah, thank you for
bringing up that question because it's important to clarify, it's only within
the world of טומאה Tumah and טהרה, Taharah, where there's something is
susceptible to become טמא tamei and even there, even if it's not
food, as soon as you plan on eating it, you make it
food.
For the כשרות Kashrut world, of course, everything that's not כשר kosher.
remains not כשר. kosher It's considered food. So, assuming within the כשרות
Kashrut world it's considered food, the question is that when you move
to the טומאה וטהרה Tumah and Taharah world, do you draw on
those like different כשרות Kashrut standards in terms of defining it? But
you can't use say, oh, it's not food for טומאה וטהרה, Tumah
and Taharah, it's not food for כשרות, Kashrut, because then it would
basically, you know, it would undermine as you're saying, you know, a
lot of things that are not כשר kosher we'd say, you know,
we would say aren't a problem. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, ah, so here you see that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
at the end of the ברייתא Baraita of this משנה, Mishnah, which
means that at the beginning, when we say a carcass of a
non-כשר kosher animal is not food, that's not רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
So we do not say that's the רבנן Rabbanan who argue with
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And we don't say that by virtue of
it being forbidden, that makes it considered food. We do not say
that. So, גמרא Gemara says, all right, throw that whole thing out.
You're right. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, you're right. דכולי עלמא
לא אמרינן איסורו חשיבותו. Dechulei alma lo amrinan issuro chashivuto.
You've proved your point. Nobody says by virtue of something being forbidden
that automatically gives it the definition of food. Okay. Now, now we're
back to, so now that we threw that whole thing out, we're
back to our question. Our question was רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
the donkey is not considered to be food, so that shows you
that according to him, the broken-necked donkey is forbidden מן ההנאה. min
ha'hana'ah. And we're trying to see if we can get out of
that proof. So we tried a whole way by saying because people
don't eat donkey meat, but then we rejected that. So we said
that's not what's going on, because that wouldn't be debatable. So what
is the issue? So here's the issue. ואי דארציה מריש, Ve'ee de'artzeih
me'areish, if you broke the neck, הכי נמי, Hachi nami, then you
would be right that that would not be what do you call
it? That it would not be, oh, we're back to that, everybody
would agree that it would not be food because people don't eat
donkey meat. Go back to people don't eat donkey meat, and everybody
would agree that the fact it's forbidden does not make it food.
So if it was a dead broken-necked donkey, everybody would agree it
would not be food. So what's the debate? הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha
bemai askinan, what are we talking about? Top of י"ט עמוד ב'.
Yud Tet Amud Bet. כגון ששחטו והתלמד בו. Kegon sheshachto vehitlamed bo.
You שחט-ed shacht the donkey for practice. You wanted to practice your
שחיטה. shechitah. You didn't want to ruin a nice כשר kosher cow.
Since you wouldn't be able to eat the donkey meat anyway, you
שחט-ed shacht the donkey and then you would sell it to the
non-Jews. Okay. So you שחט-ed shacht the donkey for שחיטה shechitah practice.
And what's the issue? The issue is like this. So here again,
we are trying to resist saying that it has to do with
the fact that it is a special פטר חמור peter chamor broken-necked
donkey and forbidden in benefit and that's the debate of is it
food or not. So we're saying here, no, it's your normal donkey.
Your normal donkey, so what's the debate of whether it's food? Because
everybody said that normal people don't eat donkey, okay, and the fact
that it's forbidden doesn't make it food. So what makes this donkey
into food? So the fact is because you happen to have שחט-ed
shacht it. Now, if you שחט-ed shacht it because you were really
planning on eating it and violate, the fact that you שחט-ed shacht
it with the intention to eat it even though it's a donkey,
that would be like you intended to eat it. That makes it
food. But you didn't שחט shecht to eat it, you שחט-ed shacht
to practice your שחיטה. shechitah.
But you still did an act of שחיטה shechitah on it. Would
that, having done an act of שחיטה, shechitah, be enough to make
it into
food?
Okay. ובפלוגתא דנימוס ורבי אליעזר. Uveflugta deNimos veRabbi Eliezer. It's the debate
of נימוס Nimos and רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא, Detanya, we learn
in a ברייתא, Baraita, אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yossi, סח לי
נימוס, Sach li Nimos, אחי של רבי יהושע הגרסי, achi shel Rabbi
Yehoshua HaGarsi, interesting names we normally don't hear, whispered to me נימוס,
Nimos, the brother of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua the הגרסי, Garsi, שהשוחט
את העורב והתלמד בו, shehashochet et ha'orev vehitlamed bo,
if somebody שחט-ed shacht a raven to practice their שחיטה, shechitah, דמו
מכשיר. damo machshir. The blood, remember, blood of שחיטה shechitah is a
liquid that makes food susceptible to become טמא. tamei. So although this
is a שחיטה shechitah of a non-כשר kosher animal and it wasn't
done even with the purpose of שחיטה, shechitah, just the purpose of
practice, since it was an act of שחיטה, shechitah, the blood is
considered to make things susceptible, it's a liquid. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, דם שחיטה לעולם מכשיר. dam
shechitah le'olam machshir.
Blood of שחיטה shechitah always makes things susceptible. So isn't that exactly
what we just said? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer היינו תנא קמא,
hainu tanna kamma, that's the whole point, that it's blood of שחיטה,
shechitah, it makes things susceptible. אלא דאיסורו חשיבותו איכא בינייהו. Ella de'issuro
chashivuto ika beineiyhu.
We're back to that, but we don't mean the same thing by
it now. Its forbidden status makes it significant. But we mean something
different. Here's what we mean. תנא קמא סבר, Tanna kamma savar, דמו
מכשיר לעלמא, damo machshir le'alma,
that yes, I'll admit to you the first one said the blood,
when you שחט-ed shacht this raven, the שחיטה shechitah blood, that makes
it a liquid for other things. It's שחיטה shechitah blood, although it's
a non-כשר kosher, animal, a שחיטה shechitah was done to it. שחיטה
Shechitah blood makes other things susceptible. That's a different question. אבל לגופיה,
Aval legufeih, how about the raven itself that you just שחט-ed? shacht
Is that considered food? No. במחשבה, Bemachshavah, a raven is not כשר,
people don't eat ravens, just because you שחט-ed shacht the raven doesn't
make the raven food. The שחיטה shechitah can make the blood be
considered שחיטה shechitah blood to make things susceptible. That's a different question.
That question was on what are considered liquids to make things susceptible.
But to make the, that doesn't mean we consider the raven food,
that the raven now is susceptible even though you did an act
of שחיטה shechita on it. ואתא רבי אליעזר למימר Ve'ata Rabbi Eliezer
lemeimar comes along רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and he says, דם שחיטה
לעולם מכשיר, dam shechita le'olam machshir,
the blood of שחיטה shechita always makes things susceptible, ואפילו לגופיה, ve'afillu
legufei,
it makes the raven itself susceptible. Once you did a שחיטה shechita
even though it was only practice, and even though a שחיטה shechita
is a non-kosher bird, the fact that you did a שחיטה shechita
on it makes it susceptible. So now we are saying, so, ואפילו
לגופיה נמי בלא מחשבה, ve'afillu legufei nami belo machshava,
it does not need intention. So now we are saying like this,
it's a little crazy you have to admit, because the משנה mishna
said, the whole place we started is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon has
a list of things that were forbidden in benefit and said they're
not considered food. And one of those things was the broken-neck donkey,
which is a pretty loud statement that the broken-neck donkey for רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon once you get around to breaking the neck is
forbidden in benefit. Now we're saying that's not what it's about at
all, the donkey case, it's not only the broken-neck donkey, it's all
donkeys. And not only is it all donkeys because normal people don't
eat donkey meat, but it's a very special case of having שחט
shechted the donkey for practice. Okay, that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is talking about when he mentions the donkey. And therefore רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon is saying, oh, even though you שחט shechted it for
practice, since it's donkey meat and normal people don't eat donkey meat,
it's not food. And the rabbis say, normally I would agree with
you, the fact that you שחט shechted it for practice, even though
normally donkey meat isn't food, that makes it food. Okay, so we're
trying to squeeze that whole thing into, you know, this statement where
all it seems like you're debating is the fact that donkey is
the special donkey is forbidden in benefit. Anyway, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says like this: ממאי, Mimay,
who told you that's the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
this נימוס? Nimos? דילמא טעמא דרבי אליעזר התם דשאני עורב דאית ביה
סימני טהרה? Dilma ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer hatam deshani oreiv de'it bei simanei
tahara? Maybe, remember a point we mentioned before, one of the things
that contributes to considering this raven food is not just that you
did a שחיטה shechita although it was a practice שחיטה, shechita, but
it was the combination of the practice שחיטה shechita and that a
raven has some kosher סימנים. simanim. It's not kosher, but it has
some of the kosher סימנים simanim of the characteristics. ומנלן דסימני טהרה
מילתא היא? Umenalan desimanei tahara milta hi? And how do I know
that that's relevant? Because of what we said just a minute ago.
דתניא עלה דהא, Detanya ala deha, we taught a minute ago, אמר
רבי שמעון מה טעם הואיל ואית בו סימני טהרה? amar Rabbi Shimon
ma ta'am ho'il ve'it bo simanei tahara? Why did רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon say do I consider like pork and other types of things
and camel, why do I consider those to be food if they
even their corpses? Because they have some kosher סימנים. simanim. So you
see that's relevant. וכי תימא, Vekhi teima,
unless you say, אם משום סימני טהרה, im mishum simanei tahara, if
it's because of the raven has kosher סימנים, simanim, מאי איריא לשחטיה,
mai irya lishchatei, why are we talking that you שחט shechted it
for practice? אפילו לשאציי נמי, Afillu lishatsei nami,
even if you just, you know, שחט shechted it even totally accidentally,
even if it was just a corpse, right? If we're trying to
say the issue here is that the kosher, the
some aspects of some kosher characteristics is enough to make it food,
then it's not, how do you combine, you don't need to combine
that with the practice שחיטה. shechita. Right, before רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
said that what? That if a pig died or a camel died
and it's a total corpse, it still is considered food because these
animals have some kosher characteristics. So if that's true, say the same
thing by the raven. You would not need to combine it with
this idea of practice שחיטה. shechita. So the גמרא Gemara says, you
know what, you're right. You know what, אין הכי נמי, ein hachi
nami, you're right, that really according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
says that the raven is considered food, it has nothing to do
with the practice שחיטה. shechita. It only has to do with the
fact that it has some kosher characteristics. Why did we mention the
practice שחיטה? shechita? ומשום נימוס, Umishum Nimos, because נימוס Nimos disagreed. He
said that the raven is not food and is not susceptible. And
therefore he would say that with if, and therefore he said, but
I will admit that if you do a practice שחיטה, shechita, the
blood becomes a considered a, you know, a liquid to make things
susceptible.
But for something else.
For something else. Okay. So we are really sort of way, way
digressing. Again, the whole point is that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
that a list of things that are forbidden in benefit, lists the
broken-neck donkey, which is a pretty clear statement that he admits by
the broken-neck donkey. We're trying to get out of it. The first
way we got out of it was saying it has nothing to
do with the broken-neck donkey, it has to do with people don't
eat donkey meat, and do we say that since it's forbidden it
makes it implicitly food? We rejected that. Now we're saying, okay, but
still, nothing to do with the broken-neck donkey, general fact that people
don't eat donkey meat, but the debate of whether it's food or
not is it's a very, very special case where you שחט shechted
it for practice. And does practice שחיטה shechita enough to make donkey
meat, which people don't normally eat, enough to make it considered food?
Again, that's totally missing from that משנה, mishna, from that ברייתא, braita,
whatever, but that's what we're trying to read into it. Okay, then
the גמרא Gemara says you can't even say that because we don't
even know that that's really a debate, whether practice שחיטה shechita makes
something food or not. That might be the debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and נימוס, Nimos, but it might not. So we still,
we still are, you know, resisting this way of getting out of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So let's keep on going. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
איתיבי, eitvei, I'll ask you, לא רצה לשחוט. lo ratza lishchot. I'm
going to try to prove whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees or
doesn't agree. And now we get, thankfully we're able to leave all
that טומאה וטהרה tumah v'tahara stuff behind and try to get straight
back to the question of does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon admit or
not after the neck is broken that it's forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah.
So let's take a look. לא רצה לפשטו. Lo ratza lifshato. A
person did not want to redeem the donkey. ערפו בקופיץ מאחורה. Arfo
bekupitz me'achora. You break its neck with a קופיץ, kupitz, which is
I think a hatchet. How do they translate קופיץ kupitz over there?
A cleaver. Cleaver. Cleaver and a hatchet essentially the same. It's like
a big, it's like a big single, a big sharp-bladed knife, right?
Okay, anyway, so okay, from the back. וקוברו ואסור בהנאה. Vekovro ve'assur
behana'ah. And you bury it and you can't derive benefit. דברי רבי
יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי שמעון מתיר. Rabbi Shimon matir. So now,
after that whole big convoluted thing of טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'tahara, which
got us all confused, we're now able to like bring direct evidence
to this question. Here it says you broke the neck of the
donkey, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you don't get benefit, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says you can derive benefit. So it seems very clear
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not agree after you break the
neck. He says you're still allowed to get benefit. מותר. Mutar. So
מתיר. matir. So the גמרא Gemara says אימא ומחיים אסור בהנאה רבי
שמעון מתיר. Eima umeichayim assur behana'ah Rabbi Shimon matir. You could know,
you could sort of massage the text and say that what it
really means when they say it's forbidden in benefit, they're not talking
about after you broke the neck, they're talking about before. Here's how
you break the neck. By the way, before you broke the neck,
it was forbidden in benefit and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it
was permissible, which is admittedly a stretch. So now the גמרא Gemara
says one minute. והא מדסיפא מחיים הוי רישא לאו מחיים. Veha mideiseifa
meichayim havei, reisha lav meichayim. One minute, the end of that ברייתא
braita has them debating about the status when the donkey is alive,
which implies that here the debate is about when it's dead. דתני
סיפא, De'tani seifa, we taught at the end, לא ימיתנו, lo yamitenu,
you should not break the neck. לא בקנה, Lo bekaneh, not with
a reed, ולא במגל, velo bemagal, and not with like a scythe,
ולא בקרדום, velo bekardom, which is I don't know, a hammer, ולא
במגירה, velo bemagera, which is a saw,
ולא יכניסנו לכיפה וינעל דלת לפניה בשביל שתמות, velo yachnisenu lechevah veyin'ol
dalta lefaneha bishvil shetamut, and do not lock it in a door
and starve it dies. You specifically, it's not just about killing it,
it's a specific way of breaking of the neck. That's when you
break the neck. ואסור בגיזה ועבודה, Ve'assur begiza ve'avoda, and while it's
still alive, you cannot derive benefit. You cannot shear it or work
it. דברי רבי יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says, רבי שמעון מתיר, Rabbi Shimon matir, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
allows. So here clearly they're talking about can you benefit from it
while it's alive. So therefore the debate before where they're saying is
it permissible or forbidden was after you killed it. Which and it
shows that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that even after you killed
it, it's permissible. So the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara
says, no, that's not necessarily a proof. רישא וסיפא מחיים, Reisha veseifa
meichayim, I could say both of those are debates about whether it
is alive, can you derive benefit. So why do we have to
talk about it twice? רישא בהנאת דמיו סיפא בהנאת גופו. Reisha behana'at
damav, seifa behana'at gufo. There are two ways of deriving benefit. One
way is making money off of it. How do you make money
off of it? You sell it or you rent it. Okay, the
other is you derive direct benefit from it. You work it, you
ride on it, you shear it, I don't know if you can
shear donkeys, whatever. You work it to get direct benefit. Direct benefit
is obviously more problematic than indirect monetary benefit. So therefore we're saying
yes, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree after you kill it it's
forbidden. Why does it say twice that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows
you to derive benefit? Not that one is talking after it's killed,
but to tell you he allows both types of benefit. Not only
benefit of indirect like selling it, but even direct benefit like using
it and riding on it. Okay, so
וצריכא, utzricha, and you need to tell me both. דאי תנא הנאת
דמיו, De'ei tana hana'at damav, if you just told me you could
derive monetary benefit by selling it or renting it, בהא קשרי רבי
שמעון, bahu kashari Rabbi Shimon, maybe that's the only case רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon allows. Because it's less direct. אבל בהנאת גופו, Aval behana'at
gufo, direct benefit from use, from using it, אימא מודי ליה לרבי
יהודה, eima modei leh leRabbi Yehuda, maybe he would agree to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that that is forbidden. דאי תנא הנאת גופו, De'ei
tana behana'at gufo, if he had just said that he permits direct
benefit, then I would have said okay, maybe that's where רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda disagrees. בהא קאסר רבי יהודה, Behi kassur Rabbi Yehuda, that's
where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees. אבל
בהנאת דמיו אימא מודי ליה לרבי שמעון, Aval behana'at damav eima modei
leRabbi Shimon, but maybe by monetary benefit he agrees that that's permissible.
צריכא, Tzricha, you need both. So now what do we have? It's
really, I mean, we had a very long and difficult גמרא, Gemara,
but the point is like this. We really have two different indications
in terms of the Tannaitic material about whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
agrees after it's been killed. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon clearly says that
while it's alive it's permitted in benefit and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says it's not. What's the story after you kill it? So on
the one hand, we had רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon include the broken-neck
donkey in his list of things forbidden in benefit. That seems to
be a very clear statement. And the גמרא Gemara had all these
convoluted ways of saying oh no no maybe it's this very very
special case and it's about donkey meat and it's not about forbidden
in benefit and what not. Okay, so that's us seems like a
force and a stretch and it seems very clear that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon said that it was forbidden in benefit. But here you
have a ברייתא braita which seems very clear the opposite. It's explicit,
right? It says you broke the neck. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
forbidden, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says permissible. So the גמרא Gemara
here also tries to get out of it and say, no, no,
no, maybe permissible means before you killed it. But really what you
have is two separate Tannaitic material, one where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
sounds very clear that it's forbidden, he lists it among things forbidden
in benefit, and one where he says very clearly, you broke its
neck, it's permissible in benefit. So one of them has to be
reinterpreted. And that's why we're having these stretches of interpretation in one
case or the other, because these two Tannaitic material are very explicitly
contradicting one another. Okay, and now we're going to see a whole
different list of אמוראים, Amora'im, what do they feel רבי שמעון's Rabbi
Shimon position is after the neck is broken. Okay, yes.
You know, the donkey, I don't know if I'm mistaken here, but
the donkey was the one who told
this
individual who was going to curse the Jewish people,
right, right, right. In a way, the donkey was almost holy.
Well, the breaking of the neck is only a fine for somebody
who's not doing what you're supposed to do with the donkey. What
you're supposed to do is redeem it and give the value to
the כהן, Kohen, and actually that gives it a special positive status.
The גמרא Gemara before said that why is a donkey singled out?
It gave the reason because the donkeys as beasts of burden helped
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael take the wealth out of מצרים, Mitzrayim, you
know, and helped them in the whole act of the Exodus. So
the breaking of the neck is not that the donkey is bad.
I mean, it starts with the fact that the donkey has a
special status and it's part of this act of redemption and it's
part of what gets given to a כהן. Kohen. It's a punishment
for somebody who refuses to do it. I mean, why the donkey
has to suffer as a result, I don't know, but anyway, but
that's not the intended end of this donkey here.
No other non-kosher animal has a ritual purpose.
That's a good question. Do you do any ritual thing with any
non-kosher animal? I don't think so. Yeah, that's a good point. That's
a good point. Okay,
well, you use bee honey for ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay, so
that's not an animal. There you go. Okay, so anyway, okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So now we understand what we're up against in terms of רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position. One basically Tannaitic material saying very clearly that
it is not, that it's forbidden in benefit, and the other saying
very clearly it's permissible, and one of them has to be somehow
re-read. So that's what we're up against. וכן אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה מודה רבי שמעון לאחר עריפה שהוא אסור. Vechein amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha modeh Rabbi Shimon le'achar arifah shehu
assur. And similarly said רב נחמן Rav Nachman like what רבה Rabbah
had said, similar to רבה, Rabbah, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does
agree after the breaking of the neck that it's forbidden. ואמר רב
נחמן מנא אמינא לה, Ve'amar Rav Nachman mena amina lah, where do
I know this from? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita,
וערפתה, Ve'araftah, you shall break its neck. נאמר כאן עריפה ונאמר להלן
עריפה, Ne'emar kan arifah vene'emar lehallan arifah, it says by the donkey
break its neck, it says by the calf, עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah,
break the neck. מה להלן אסור אף כאן אסור, Mah lehallan assur
af kan assur, the same way over there it is forbidden, the
broken neck calf, אף כאן אסור, af kan assur, here too it's
forbidden. That's a Tannaitic statement that it's forbidden after the neck is
broken. Now it doesn't tell you, is it רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
is it רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who is saying that? But he
says, I've got to assume that's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, because for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that's an obvious point, it was forbidden beforehand,
of course it's forbidden afterwards. So it says, מאן, Man, who is
this? אילימא רבי יהודה, Ilima Rabbi Yehuda, if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, מחיים מי שרי, mechayyim mi sharei,
it's already forbidden from life. Why do I need to learn from
a verse that it's forbidden after you break the neck? אלא לאו
רבי שמעון היא, Ella lav Rabbi Shimon hi, so it must be
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So here you have a ברייתא Baraita saying
it's forbidden when you break the neck. It's the only person who
could be saying this is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and therefore that
proves to me that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon admits. אמר ליה רב
ששת ספרא, Amar lei Rav Sheshet Safra, רב ששת ספרא, Rav Sheshet
Safra,
interesting, the scribe, said to him, חברך תרגמוה, Chavrach targemuha,
your friends, your colleagues have explained that, לעולם רבי יהודה, Le'olam Rabbi
Yehuda, that could be רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So why do I
need it? Don't I already know it's forbidden? ואיצטריך, Ve'itztarich, no, I
need it to tell me it remains forbidden after you break the
neck. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atach amina, I would have thought to
say, עריפה במקום פדיה עומדת. Arifah bimkom pidyah omedet. What are you
supposed to do with this donkey? You're supposed to redeem it with
a sheep. What happens when you redeem it with a sheep? It
becomes permissible. So maybe if you don't redeem it with a sheep
and you do this other ritual of breaking the neck, that's a
substitute ritual for redeeming it. So the same way redeeming it removes
its status, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
said it was forbidden before, and he says redeeming it removes the
status. So the same way redeeming it removes the status according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so therefore breaking of the neck would also
remove the status, I might have thought. מה פדיה מתרת, Mah pidyah
materet, the same way redeeming removes the status according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, אף עריפה מתרת, af arifah materet, breaking of the neck
also, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, and therefore the verse tells
me no, that even though redeeming removes the status, breaking of the
neck it remains forbidden. So yes, you have a ברייתא Baraita that
says breaking of the neck it's forbidden, but it's not necessarily רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, maybe it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and maybe it's
there to tell me that even when you do the ritual, it
remains forbidden. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
רב נחמן מנא אמינא לה, Amar Rav Nachman mena amina lah, so
רב נחמן Rav Nachman though is not giving up. He says I'll
prove it to you from another place. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraita, דתני לוי, Detani Levi, לוי Levi taught, הוא הפסיד
ממונו של כהן לפיכך יופסד ממונו. Hu hifsid mamono shel Kohen lefikach
yufsad mamono. Here's a nice way of articulating the point of breaking
the neck of the donkey. You tried to cheat out the כהן,
Kohen, you did not want to redeem the donkey with a sheep
and give a sheep to the כהן. Kohen. So you wanted to
cheat out the כהן, Kohen, your money is going to be destroyed
as a result. You'll lose out. You tried to make the כהן
Kohen lose out. you lose out, we'll kill the donkey. So money.
Now of course the assumption is if you're losing out because you
broke the neck, the assumption is that why did, how did you
lose out? Because it becomes forbidden in benefit. You can't use it
at all. Okay, so money, who is this going like? אילימא רבי
יהודה, Ilei'ma Rabbi Yehuda, if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, המפסיד וקאי,
hamfsid veka'ei, it was already forbidden in benefit. Breaking of the neck
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda did not make it any more
forbidden in benefit, right? רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the donkey starts by
being forbidden in benefit. So you say, ah, you tried to cheat
out the כהן, kohen, you're going to lose out, we're going to
break its neck. You already couldn't derive benefit, so what difference does
it make if you break the neck or not? It's forbidden in
benefit. So you're already, so you're
already it's a, הא נפסיד וקאי, ha nifsid veka'ei, you're already at
a loss. אלא לאו רבי שמעון היא, Ella lav Rabbi Shimon hi,
it must be רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it must be saying it
was permissible in benefit. You're trying to cheat out the כהן, kohen,
therefore we're going to break its neck and make it forbidden. So
you see, according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, once you break the
neck, it is forbidden. The גמרא Gemara says, that is not a
proof. אי בעית אימא I ba'is eima if you want I can
say רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אי בעית אימא I ba'is eima רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. This idea that we're punishing you works according to
both approaches. How does it work? אי בעית אימא I ba'is eima
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it works like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אפסידי
דביני וביני, afsidei de-beini u-beini, because it's true when you have the
donkey and it was alive, you couldn't derive benefit, but you could
still gain from it. How could you gain? That you would give
a sheep that would be worth half of the donkey to the
כהן. kohen. The donkey is worth a hundred, you give a fifty
dollar sheep to the כהן, kohen, and now you benefit fifty dollars,
at least you know retain fifty dollars. Once we kill the donkey,
you're out the whole hundred dollars. So even according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, you lose when the donkey gets killed because you're not
able to retain for yourself the difference between the value of the
sheep and the donkey. So for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda number one,
there's a loss when the donkey gets killed. And not only that,
אי בעית אימא I ba'is eima רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, for רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon there's even if the donkey is permissible in benefit,
here it's obvious. Let's say after you broke the neck it's permissible
in benefit. Why do you lose out when we break its neck?
Why do you lose out?
If because it becomes forbidden in benefit.
No, no, no, if it's we're trying to say according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon it could be permissible in benefit. Why would you
still lose out?
Oh, because a live donkey is
worth more than a dead donkey. Yeah, a live donkey is worth
more than a dead donkey. So it doesn't have to be forbidden
in benefit in order to say that you're losing out. Okay, so
the פחת מיתה, p'chat mita, because how about the devaluation of death?
So therefore the idea that you lose out by us breaking the
neck, A, is a relevant statement even according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that it was forbidden before and after, and could also work
even if it's permissible before and after. There's a loss that is
incurred once the neck is broken. Yes.
Did you say even for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda if you redeemed
it with a sheep then it is permissible in benefit?
Yes, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. The standard way it
works is the donkey starts as forbidden. As long as it's alive
you can redeem it with a sheep, then and the result is
then it becomes permissible. That's all what he originally so this
whole statement about it's forbidden in benefit means if you didn't redeem
it.
Exactly, yes.
When I first saw the text when it said it's a loss,
I first thought of a בית דין Beit Din saying you haven't
redeemed it, I'm going to declare it הפקר hefker so it's not
yours anymore.
הפקר? hefker? No, no, no. What it means is it's explaining the
logic between the תורה's Torah מצוה mitzvah of breaking the neck. That's
the only point that it's coming to do. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, רבי יוחנן ותימא רבי אלעזר אמר, Rabbi Yochanan ve-teima Rabbi Elazar
amar, so anyway so here we have everybody that says רב נחמן
Rav Nachman and רבא Rava that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees after
breaking of the neck, although the proofs weren't proofs. Now we're going
to have opposing voices. רבי יוחנן ותימא רבי אלעזר אמר, Rabbi Yochanan
ve-teima Rabbi Elazar amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan some say רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar say, עדיין היא מחלוקת. adayin hi machloket. No, that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon even after the neck is broken still says that
it is permissible in benefit. The debate is before the neck is
broken and after the neck is broken. In both cases רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says it's permissible. איכא דמתני להא דרב נחמן, Ika de-masni
la-hada de-Rav Nachman, some teach the teaching of רב נחמן Rav Nachman
that says that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon admits after the fact, אהא
אהא, aha aha, on the following
משנה. mishna. המקדש בפטר חמור אינה מקודשת. Hamakadesh be-peter chamor einah mekudeshet.
If a man tries to marry a woman with the firstborn donkey
as his instead of a ring, very romantic, it does not work.
Why not? Because it's forbidden in benefit. Okay, fine.
לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי שמעון, Leima matnitin de-lo ke-Rabbi Shimon, and we
said that sounds like it's not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, because רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says the donkey is permissible in benefit, so he
would be able to marry her with the donkey. So אמר רב
נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, and here רב נחמן Rav Nachman comes in
and says, אמר רבה בר אבוה, amar Rabba bar Avuha, לאחר עריפה
ודברי הכל. le-achar arifa ve-divrei hakol. No, it could be רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, but it could be after you broke the neck of
the donkey, and then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would admit that it's
forbidden in benefit. So it's basically the same point that רב נחמן
Rav Nachman comes with the assumption or the position that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon admits after the neck is broken it's forbidden in benefit,
and he just is saying that some say the original context of
that statement was explaining this משנה mishna of marrying a woman with
this donkey, and that he said that that could even be רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Why? Because it's after the neck is broken and
then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon admits. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, some say,
הא מני, ha mani, who is this? One minute, forget the רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda debate. This משנה mishna doesn't
make sense. לא רבי יהודה ולא רבי שמעון, Lo Rabbi Yehuda ve-lo
Rabbi Shimon, it doesn't work according to either opinion. Why can't you
marry a woman with this donkey? אי רבי שמעון, Ei Rabbi Shimon,
first of all according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, תיקדש בכוליה, tiktash
be-kulei, the whole value
is... Even according to
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda that says you can't derive benefit, there still
is value in this donkey, right? We just said, what's the value
in this donkey according to רבי יהודה? Rebbe Yehuda? Even though you
can't derive benefit, as long as it's alive, what can you do?
Redeem it. Redeem it with a sheep that costs less money and
you benefit the difference. So even according to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
there's a benefit, there's value in this donkey. אי רבי יהודה, Ei
Rebbe Yehuda, תקדש בההוא הנאה דביני ביני, tikdash b'hahu hana'ah d'beini beini,
marry the woman with the value, the difference between the value of
the donkey and the value of a sheep.
So, אמר רבא בר אבוה אמר רב, Amar Rava bar Avuha amar
Rav, לעולם רבי יהודה, l'olam Rebbe Yehuda, is רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda.
Why can't you therefore marry this woman? There's some value difference between
the value of the donkey and the value of a sheep. וכגון
שאינו שוה אלא שקל, u'kegon she'eino shaveh ela shekel, we're talking about
a donkey that is really like, I don't know, it's deformed or
whatever it is, it's only worth a שקל. shekel. And now, okay,
it might only be worth a שקל, shekel, but you could redeem
it with a sheep that's worth a half a שקל. shekel. So
now we're going to say there is a minimum of the value
of a sheep. A sheep cannot be less than a שקל. shekel.
So it's a special case of a donkey that is so, you
know, cheap, that is so worthless, that you cannot get any benefit
from it because any sheep, because the minimum a sheep, the sheep
value would not be less, would be equal or greater to that
of the donkey.
Okay, וסבר לה כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, v'savar lah k'Rebbe Yosi b'Rebbe
Yehuda, and he holds like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rebbe Yosi b'Rebbe
Yehuda.
Where were we?
דתניא, d'tanya, it says in a ברייתא, braita, תפדה תפדה, tifdeh tifdeh,
it says two פסוקים pesukim that you should redeem a donkey with
a sheep. תפדה מיד, tifdeh miyad, number one, you can do it
right away, you don't have to wait till it's thirty days old,
it's not like a human baby. ותפדה כל שהוא, v'tifdeh kol shehu,
you can redeem it even if the sheep is worth, is worth
next to nothing. That's the first point. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר,
Rebbe Yosi b'Rebbe Yehuda omer, no, אין פדיה פחותה משקל, ein pidyah
p'chuta mi'shekel, you the sheep cannot be worth less than a שקל.
shekel. Okay, and therefore, we will, what, why don't we end here?
We'll pick up with this tomorrow. But the basic point is that
therefore it is possible that there is no value to this donkey.
You can't say you can always find a cheaper sheep because according
to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rebbe Yosi b'Rebbe Yehuda, there's a minimum
value of the sheep of a שקל. shekel. And if the donkey
is worth less than a שקל, shekel, then there's literally no benefit,
no value of the donkey. We end with still not having resolved,
or having a debate of, hey, it sounds like a debate of
משניות, mishnayot, and certainly a debate of the אמוראים, Amoraim, whether רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon agrees after the neck is broken. While it's alive,
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says it's forbidden in benefit, רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon says it's permissible. Once the neck is broken, there there's a
debate. Will רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon finally agree there that it's forbidden,
like an עגלה ערופה, egla arufa, is that the ultimate punishment for
you, that its neck is broken and it's worthless? Or even there,
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says there's a ritual of breaking the neck,
but the animal still remains permissible in benefit? That remains a debate
of the אמוראים. Amoraim.